welcome to meditating with john viveki
we live stream every weekday morning at
9 30 a.m eastern times
monday uh alternating between a new
lesson we call the dharma day which we
had
uh yesterday and a review of the whole
ecology of practices called
papaya day the pi day also announced our
alternatingly
a review of the ecology drawn from the
eastern traditions
and the ecology drawn from the western
generations
a reminder that you're not expected to
learn the whole thing
or practice the whole thing that's not
the point the point is to give you a
rich
repertoire and reservoir of practices
and then using the principles of design
you build an ecology of practices so
that it will
suit you but it will also fit into the
sangha
so for if you're joining us for the
first time and that sounded all
confusing please don't worry
um i invite you to continue to meet with
us but
go uh in the description uh for links to
previous lessons and sets
immediately do lesson one and then do
one or two lessons every week as you
continue to meet with us
and you will very quickly integrate with
the sangha
i would ask everybody to please help me
to help as many people as possible
by liking the stream to increase its
visibility in the youtube algorithm
at the end of every session there is
a q a please limit the questions to
uh anything from the ecology of practice
either
from the eastern or western traditions
you can ask for many lessons in the
course
we give priority to questions from the
western traditions on monday wednesdays
and fridays
those days also tend to go a little bit
longer and uh priority to
questions uh from the eastern traditions
uh sorry for
yes from the eastern traditions on
tuesdays and thursdays a reminder that
in addition to questions
uh it's very welcome to share
observations comments
edifications uh an announcement
um i realize this is fairly short term
but there will be no class
this thursday there will be no class to
thursday
i will not be here this thursday i
encourage everybody to meet on the
discord server
and to do a session now all right so
last time i went over the epicurean
stuff i said i was going to review it
today but i'm actually going to put that
off so we can get into the meditation
have some time for a question
and i'll do a review on wednesday and
that way the review will also lead in
to completing uh the lesson that we're
only sort of halfway through on
wednesday
reminder that this week we're actually
having three dharma days monday
wednesday and friday one more time
please remember
there will be no class on thursday
please meet on the discord server
all right so if you have more general
questions
a reminder that every uh third friday of
the month
at 3 p.m eastern time we live stream on
youtube
on the general q a and you're most
welcome there
we did this last friday and we have
quite a few people here from the sangha
and that always enriches things so thank
you very much
all right so please get yourself into
position set your phones to do not
disturb
we will begin as always with some
chanting and then
we will go into the silent set we'll
come out and we'll
take some questions share some
observations um
etc we will all begin together
when i say begin
[Music]
begin
one
[Music]
oh
one
on
um
[Music]
one
on
[Laughter]
[Music]
one begin your silences
you
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communities
perhaps by reciting the five promises
just remember that uh we are moving to
our
this the question shuttle monday
wednesdays and fridays emphasizing
uh the western traditions and tuesdays
and thursdays the eastern traditions
a request again to you in addition to
sharing questions which are
observations and edifications
uh final reminder uh that will will
typically be going longer
on monday wednesdays and fridays
so tech one uh soho what to do about
itches
so the thing to do about itches they
come up frequently
and um and so typical
discussion um so
wherever the itch is step back label it
um treat it as
a form of resistance distraction
so when it comes up
step back label it and then apply the
five factors
of inquiring mindfulness
remembering the principles if it goes
away
if if it goes away don't think oh
sort of oh look at my magical powers
return to following your breath
if you go away if you're distracted from
your distraction by distraction
um label that distraction and then
return to your breath
don't do any more five factors of
inquiring mindfulness
just label that distraction return to
your breath if the
itch doesn't go away and you don't go
away
and you're applying the five factors of
acquiring mindfulness to it
if it gets to a point where it is
overwhelming you and you are no longer
being educated you are merely enduring
and awake come out of it your eyes
if needed if not right keep your eyes
closed
and mindful let's see my h is on my leg
and mindfully
scratch important point about the
mindfulness is
notice that if in the moment you
acquiesce
to address the itch it goes away
that will frequently happen and that
tells you the nature of the itch
the itch the itch distraction isn't
because
we don't quite know what causes itching
in the first place but
right those kinds of itches that go away
once you
acquiesce to break the
meditation and return your awareness in
some sense
to the world
those itches
i i don't want to i don't want to use
too harsh for language but they're
basically sort of
they're tricks right of of the habitual
ego
their tricks of resistance their ways of
undermining your commitment to
developing
the habits and virtues that you're
developing now
if when you turn to address the edge and
scratch it
it doesn't go away then there was just
something there and
right you scratch it alleviate the
distress
and then return uh to your practice
so let's review again
label it as a distraction
if it's taking over the majority of your
awareness
center stage apply the five factors of
inquiring mindfulness
if you go away return to your breath
just and don't do that and don't do the
five factors on this on the secondary
distraction
just label it return to your breath if
it goes away
don't grasp it as magical power just
return to your breath
neither one of you goes away you get to
a place where you're just merely
enduring
and mindfully scratch your itch
noticing if you can if the mere act of
acquiescing to scratch makes the itch go
away
kira kroger observation i'm noticing
that some of my desires are wrapped up
in an angry super critical voice
and so sitting with that feeling is
difficult but softening which
gives me hope yes kyra i totally
uh empathize with you that is also
um that the some of these desires
um express themselves almost in a
demanding
if you say critical or harsh voice
because they are desires
that are born not just out of need
or want but they are desire we have
desires that are born
also out of hurt
and that's what i mentioned last time
about you talk about you know
desire for pleasure and fear of pain
but the desire and fear
are bound up together uh in important
ways
and so we also desire to avoid pain
and so some of our desires can often be
born out of hurt
uh and they can or they can be born
under frustration
um they can be born out of
a demand placed upon us by a sadistic
superego
um so yes um and
listening to them and being with them i
i like
i like the way it sounds to me like
you're
integrating the epicurean practice and
the mindfulness practices which is what
i encourage everybody to do
that's at the heart of sabrin for
example but the way you're you're
integrating them together is if you
if you set yourself into
the being mode to befriend that desire
in a virtuous manner it will soften
it will soften the voice will soften and
typically once the voice softens enough
the desire shifts
it's hard to describe what that feels
like but it goes from being a
it goes from being sort of a fevered
desire
to more of us like to something that you
can more
uh deeply savor when when it is
addressed
algernon females we're getting all kinds
of observations which is great
i'm finding music particularly powerful
harmony in particular
the song in particular resonates with me
very strongly
so so i thank you all i wonder what part
of the ecology practices
is calling that forth from you um maybe
it's the savoring
uh perhaps it's the reciprocal opening
in
uh meta perhaps it's prajna all of those
tend to
increase my awareness of the sheer
musicality
of the ongoing right intelligible
presence
of being but that also itself vectors
into
uh an enhancement enrichment a deepening
of my appreciation for music um
so i'm just wondering but that's
fantastic
um that deepening
of our ability to resonate
is very important when we talk about the
philosophical
uh contemplative companionships of lahav
on friday
the the the notion of resonance which
has also been
present when we talked about reciprocal
opening et cetera
in lexia divina the notion of resonance
obviously drawn for music is going to be
central so thank you for sharing that
observation
all right so i want to thank everybody
for joining
uh amara was with us today i want to
thank my dear friend and technomage
and also my beloved son jason who's also
helping out doing a lot
mars going to be away tomorrow jason's
going to be helping me
uh we're going to be having the white
board up again and continuing on with
the epicurean
and then having a sip please subscribe
to the channel to be notified of the
next video
also follow me on twitter if it's not
against any of your principles for any
updates
about these streams invite others who
might benefit by sharing this series
there is
right if you if you subscribe to this
channel and share it
people will find access there to the
lecture series awakening for the meeting
crisis and voices with verbage which is
a d logo series
um and both of those explore in depth uh
this pathway
of wisdom that we are cultivating and
walking upon together
please join the discord server to chat
with others to do the moving practices
to do an extra set
uh we're gonna have that's what we're
gonna hone some of the new practices
like the philosophical uh companionships
um on the discord server the discord
server will no doubt
home the sanga meeting for thursday when
i can't be here
so please consider joining the discord
server remember that
continuity of practice is more important
than your quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to the standard of
harsh perfectionism but virtuous
friendship
because there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body
but there is no ally no friend no true
companion on
the path better than your own minded
body
you lamps unto yourselves into each
other
take good care i'll see you tomorrow bye